The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
Kyoto (Part 2)
（島田(しまだ) 開(かい)）ああ…
なんて美しい夕日だろう
What a beautiful sunset.
The next thing I knew, I was standing with a hoe in my hand.
気が付くと
手にくわを持って立っていた
I quickly realized I was dreaming,
すぐさま 夢と気付いたが—
but I had such a sense of nostalgia that I started using it.
何だか懐かしくて
そのまま くわを振るい続けた
Someone's calling me.
誰かが呼んでる…
ああ ５年前に出ていった恋人だ
It's my girlfriend who left me five years ago.
そうか…
I see.
In the dream, we never broke up.
こっちでは
別れずに済んだんだ
Oh, that's right.
ああ… そうだ 俺…
三段リーグ抜けられなくて
故郷に戻ったんだっけ
I couldn't get past the 3-dan league, so I came back home.
It's the house's light.
家の明かりだ
I feel like I'm going to cry.
涙が出そうだ
みんな いる！
Everyone's here and doing well.
元気だ
じんちゃんも ばんちゃんも
会いたかった！
My grandma and grandpa are here too.
I missed them so much.
Dang, Kai's really good.
（島田の父）
やっぱり開は強いなー！
Nobody here can beat him.
ここじゃもう 誰もかなわんさ
He's great.
（島田の祖父）すごいな
父さん　じんちゃん　みんな…
Dad, Grandpa, everyone.
I'm really sorry.
すみませんでした…
You've been cheering me on for so long, and yet...
こんなにも長い間
応援してもらったのに…
It's all right, Kai.
（島田の祖父）ええんだよ 開
プロになんてなれなくったって
Even if you couldn't become a professional.
幸せなんてな—
Happiness is something you can find no matter where you are.
実は どこにいたって
探せるものなんだ
ただ 精いっぱい生きてりゃあ
それで ええんだ
So if you live with all your might, that's enough.
It's enough, Kai.
ええんだよ　開
The funny thing is
（島田）笑えたのは—
I was playing shogi, even in the dream.
夢の中でも将棋を指していたこと
（島田）いてて…
Ow!
Even still, I wanted to become a professional,
（島田）それでも
棋士になりたかったと悔やんで—
and I regretted it so much that I still had stomachaches.
やっぱり胃を痛めていたこと
This must be like a nightmare for Shimada, 8-dan.
（記者１）島田八段にしてみりゃ
悪夢みたいなもんだろうよ
At this rate, there's a strong possibility of him losing four times in a row.
（記者２）この調子じゃ
４タテ ストレート負けが濃いな
He probably won't have a match in his hometown.
ふるさと対決は もうねぇな
The phrase is "talking behind someone's back," but still...
（島田）陰口は陰でって
言ってもなぁ
It isn't very mature.
大人気ないしなぁ…
It'll be a pain to get them to apologize.
謝られてもめんどくさいし
（島田）ああ　胃が痛い
My stomach hurts.
All right.
さてと… そろそろ支度するか
I guess it's time to get ready.
（島田）棋士になれなくて
田舎に帰った自分
The me who couldn't become a professional and moved back to the countryside.
The me who risked everything to make it
this far and now faces four losses in a row.
全てを懸けて ここまで来ても
４タテ食らいそうな自分
Which one is a nightmare?
どっちが悪夢か…
I'll find out by seeing it through to the end!
とことん
味わってやろうじゃないか！
It's day two of the fourth match of the Lion King Tournament.
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）
獅子(しし)王戦 第四局 ２日目
On the first day, Master Souya secured
his defense and launched the first attack,
初日は—
既に守りを固めた宗谷(そうや)名人が
先攻を仕掛けるも—
but Shimada counterattacked that well
and slightly holds the dominant position.
島田さんがうまく切り返し
僅かながら優位を築き—
Shimada started to attack with N-7c,
but the match was adjourned with a sealed move.
７三桂(けい)
島田さんが
そのまま攻めに出たところで—
封じ手となった
Breakfast Lounge Hideyama
Still, don't you think Shimada's N-7c is a little too soon?
（記者３）それにしても
島田八段の７三桂は—
ちょっと前のめり過ぎでは？
Yeah, it feels more like he's panicking than ready to attack.
（記者４）
ああ 何か攻めに出るというより
焦ってるって感じですな
（従業員）
おみそ汁 いかがですか？
Would you like some miso soup?
Oh, please.
（桐山 零）あっ お願いします
He probably doesn't want to draw it out.
長引かせたくないんじゃないか？
体調も悪そうだし…
After all, he seems ill.
And still...
それにしてもなぁ
Shimada is doing his best, but nothing stands out.
島田君も頑張っとるんだが
ぱっとしないなぁ
Not against Souya.
やっぱり宗谷相手だとなぁ
I think we're looking at four straight losses.
（記者３）今回は
こりゃあ ４タテになりそうだ
So Shimada, 8-dan, will miss another showdown in his hometown.
（記者４）島田八段
また故郷対決 成らずか
Yamagata is a long way off.
山形は遠いな
（零）控え室の意見は
昨日から一貫して—
Since yesterday, the outlook in the waiting room was that Souya had this match as well.
宗谷持ち 一色だった
確かに島田さんは 今回 積極的だ
Shimada is definitely being proactive this match,
but I wouldn't call it panicking.
でも決して焦ってはいない
He's playing like normal.
至って いつもどおりだ
That's what it looks like to me.
僕には そう見える
神経戦が続いたが—
The battle of nerves continued,
島田さんは
宗谷名人相手にひるまず—
but Shimada was undaunted as he earned a few points off of Master Souya.
細かくポイントを稼いだ
It doesn't look as bad as they say.
そんなに悪くないはずだ
（通話ボタンの音）
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）桐山っ！
Kiriyama!
Why didn't you tell me Big Brother was in poor health?!
お前 兄者(あにじゃ)が体調悪いって—
なぜ俺に教えんっ？
Riiiing
Grrrr!
I would've taken him to Kyoto in a limousine with a bed!
ベッド付きのリムジンで
京都まで送ったのに！
And what's this?! You two have been practicing together?!
しかも何だっ？
ずっと二人で研究やってただと？
Why didn't you invite me?!
なぜ俺も誘わんっ？
I'm Big Brother's disciple and your senior at the workshop!
（二海堂）俺は兄者の弟弟子(でし)で
研究会ではお前の先輩なんだぞっ！
S-Sorry! I did try to contact you, but...
ご… ごめん
一応 連絡しようとはしたんだけど
Um, uh, Shimada...
（零）
えーと えーと… 島田さんが…
Please don't. He'll make a big fuss.
やめて… 大騒ぎになるから
It'd be so stressful that I'd get a hole in my stomach,
いたたまれなくて
マジで胃に穴が開くから…
so don't tell the kiddo.
坊には言わないで〜
Big Brother! Are you okay?!
（二海堂）
兄者〜っ 大丈夫ですか？
今すぐ参りますっ！
I'm on my way!
He once landed a helicopter in the courtyard of the neighborhood elementary school.
（島田）あいつ 以前
近所の小学校の校庭に—
ヘリで乗りつけたことが
あるんだってば…
I would've flown there if I hadn't had a match too.
（二海堂）
俺も対局でなければ
飛んでいったのだが…
Shogi Hall
Kiriyama, take good care of Big Brother.
桐山　兄者を頼む
終局後も ちゃんと
そばにいてくれ
Stay with him even after the match is over.
きっと兄者は
何がどうあっても—
No matter what happens,
I know he'll play to the very end.
とことんまで指すだろうから
Okay. I understand.
（零）うん　分かった
I promise I'll stay with him until he gets home.
必ず家まで送り届ける
Chairman, please, at least let me do the morning broadcast,
or let me re-adjourn the match!
（辻井(つじい)武史(たけし)）会長〜！
せめて…
せめて朝の中継だけでも！
封じ手だけでも！
I'm fine! I can do this!
大丈夫です　ちゃんとできます！
I swear!
できますから〜！
I even bought new formal wear too!
せっかく新しい和服
着てきたのに…
Let me be on TV!
テレビに出させて！
うっ うぇっ… ゴホゴホッ
Looks like one of the official observers, Tsujii, 9-dan, had the flu.
（職員１）
インフルエンザですって…
正立会人の辻井九段
They just found out and that's the result.
さっきバレて
このありさまですわ　は〜ぁ…
Everyone gargle! Disinfect your hands!
（神宮寺(じんぐうじ)崇徳(たかのり)）
全員うがい！　手の消毒！
Does anyone else have the flu?!
他にもいないか？
インフルエンザ！
Step forward!
名乗り出ろっ！
If you infect the players, I'll kill you!
対局者にうつしたら ぶっ殺すぞ！
（辻井）オッホン ゴホゴホ
Since yesterday, he's been arrogantly clearing his throat.
（職員２）いやぁ
何か昨日から オホンオホンと—
やけに威張ってるなと
思ってたんだけど
I never figured he wanted to be on TV
so badly that he was covering up a cold.
まさかテレビに映りたい一心で
かぜを隠していたとは…
I know. "A waste of good looks" describes him perfectly.
（職員３）
ほんと 残念なハンサムって
彼のためにある言葉ですよね
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）はっ
And so, Smith,
…てなわけで スミス
I'm promoting you from substitute observer to official observer!
この時間をもって
副立会人から正立会人に昇格！
What?! So suddenly?!
えっ？ い… いきなり？
But it starts in ten minutes!
10分前ですよ？
All right, go to the match room!
（神宮寺）さぁ 対局室へゴー！
And I also have to open the envelope with the sealed move?!
（三角）
しかも いきなり封じ手の開封？
そんな大役 ノー練習で？
I have to perform an important role like that with no practice?!
（行司）待ったなし！
Now or never!
Someone's Observer
My Own Title Match
And I'm an observer for someone else's
title match before I even have my own?!
（三角）…てか 俺
Someone's Observer
My Own Title Match
自分のタイトル戦より
他人の立会人が先？
Someone's Observer
My Own Title Match
What kind of foreshadowing is that?!
何のフラグっすか？
不吉すぎるんですけど！
In any case, it doesn't seem good!
It'll be fine! I promise!
（神宮寺）大丈夫！　大丈夫！
タイトル戦なんて ここにいる
ほぼ全棋士が出たことないから！
Hardly any of the professional players here have had a title match.
16th Master
Well, I have, though!
まっ 俺はあるけどねっ！
16th Master
Bam!
Glisten
Having to open the envelope with another
player's sealed move before I get my own...
自分の封じ手より
他人の封じ手の開封が先だなんて…
Glisten
It's like putting my stamp on a friend's marriage registration as a witness before getting married myself.
自分が結婚する前に—
友人の婚姻届の証人のはんこを
押しちゃった… みたいな？
Although it is an honor...
いえ めでたいんですけどね…
（三角）それでは開封いたします
I will now open the envelope.
The sealed move is S*6f.
封じ手は ６六銀(ぎん)打ち
And so, the curtain rose silently on the second day.
（零）そして—
２日目の幕が静かに上がった
And now for...
…で もってっと
Hey!
おい！ 桐山
Kiriyama!
And now, I'd like to commence the
explanation of the demonstration board
（司会）
それでは ただいまより
第二十期 獅子王戦 第四局—
for this second day of the fourth match of the 20th Lion King Tournament.
２日目の大盤解説を
始めたいと思います
First let me introduce the board commentator,
（司会）
まずは今大会の大盤解説—
Shogi Dragon Fujimoto Raidou.
藤本(ふじもと)雷堂(らいどう)棋竜
And the observer of this match, Tsujii, 9-dan, has the flu,
そして今回
立会人の辻井九段が—
何と インフルエンザということで
皆さまへの影響を考慮し—
so with our audience in mind, we acted fast and asked Kiriyama Rei, 5-dan, to provide commentary as well.
急きょ 代理で一部解説を
していただくことになりました—
桐山零 五段です
I-I'll do my best.
よっ… よろしくお願いします
Holding mic with both hands
from nervousness
As you know, Kiriyama, 5-dan,
（司会）桐山五段は
皆さまご存じのとおり—
Holding mic with both hands
from nervousness
史上５人目の
中学生プロ棋士ということで—
received a lot of attention for being the fifth junior high student to become a professional shogi player in history.
注目を集めましたが
The other four people who did that,
including Master Souya, all went on to become Masters,
中学生プロといえば—
宗谷名人をはじめ 全員が
その後 名人になっているという—
so you could say junior high professionals are future Masters in the making,
いわば未来の名人の卵であると
いえますが
but what do you think in that regard?
ご自身はその辺は？
Huh? Um, my ability is not that great
compared to my older colleagues. Sorry.
（零）へ？ あ あの…
僕は先輩たちに比べると
いきなり器が小さく…
すいません…
Of course not!
（藤本）全くだ！
Even with a junior high debut,
it becomes pointless if you take this long to get out of C1.
いくら中学生デビューでも—
いきなりＣ１で
こんなに足止め食らってりゃ—
意味がない！
I made my debut in my first year of high school,
but at his age, I was in B2.
俺は高１でデビューだが
こいつの年にはＢ２になっていた
What I'm trying to say is...
何が言いたいかというと…
I'm more impressive!
俺の方がえらい！
That's my point!
…と いうことだ！
（零）うっ ああ…
（藤本）ところが どうだ？
So then, answer me this.
Why is the world so enamored with the expression "junior high debut"?
中学生デビューという言葉だけを
世間はありがたがる！
It's confounding to me!
全くもって納得いかん！
Future Master?
“未来の名人”？
Nobody knows that!
そんなん分からんだろ！
The goal is to "become a professional,"
プロになるのが目標で—
何が何でも名人になるっていうのが
目標でなさそうなのが—
but not having the goal of "becoming a Master at all costs" is something I can't abide.
気に食わんっ！
The Japanese posit that having no desires is a rather beautiful thing,
欲がないことを日本人は
とかく美しく言い立てるが—
so why is having a goal good while having desires is bad?
目標はよくて欲はいかんて
おかしいだろ？
Isn't it strange?
そりゃ同じもんじゃないのか？
They're the same thing.
Yeah, yeah.
Blush
Relief
Yeah,
yeah
ちなみに俺はなりたい！
Incidentally, I want to become that.
What?
Shock
あの不思議ちゃんのおかげで
ずっと阻まれているが—
Although I've been held back thanks to that strange fellow,
I swear I'll drag him down and become a Master myself.
絶対に引きずり降ろして—
（藤本）名人になってやる！
（観客１）うんうん
First-timers
Veterans
Yeah, yeah.
（藤本）それまで
Ａ級から退く気は みじんもない！
Until then, you can bet the house that I'll never drop out of Class A!
And once I take a title, it's mine!
…ていうか 取ったら返さんっ！
I'll hold on to it 'til the day I die!
死ぬまで しがみついてやる！
くわーっ！
That is all!
以上っ！
I'm scared!
怖っ！
P.S. Shimada, you were surrounded by people like this and fought them daily, huh?
（零）追伸　島田さん…
あなた こんな人たちに囲まれて
日々 戦っていらしたんですね…
That you only suffer from stomachaches makes you a monster in a way!
胃痛だけで済んでること自体
ある意味 あなたも怪物ですってば
自分 無理っす！
Ａ級 無理っす！
I can't do it!
Class A is impossible!
うわぁぁ…
Kyoto (Part 2)
Kyoto (Part 3)
It hurts.
痛い…
はぁ… 痛い…
It hurts.
うっ… 痛い
くぅ… ああ 痛い…
Man, it hurts.
This is just...
全くもって 本当に… はぁっ…
Dammit!
ちっくしょ…　うう…
It's like a black bog throbbing in the pit of my stomach.
みぞおちの中で黒い沼が
どぶどぶと脈打っているようだ
（島田）
へっ 生きてるって気がするぜ
It really makes you feel alive!
P-5g+? He's going with that? It's crazy!
（関係者１）５七歩(ふ)成！
ここでいくのか？ むちゃだ！
If he lets up on the attack, he'll be surrounded!
（関係者２）攻めが切れたら
あっという間に寄せられるぞ
His own king is still on shaky ground.
（関係者３）自玉(じぎょく)がまだ不安定だ
（関係者４）
攻めがどこまで続くか…
How long can he keep up the attack?
S*6g! Threatmate!
（関係者１）６七銀　詰めろ だ！
S-7h.
（関係者２）７八銀
R-2h! Threatmate again!
（関係者３）２八飛(ひ)　また 詰めろ
Will Shimada be able to finish off the king like this?
（関係者５）
島田 このまま寄せ切れるか？
Still, his opponent is Souya.
（関係者６）しかし相手は宗谷だぞ
But will he make it?
（関係者７）いやぁ でも届くか？
He won't.
届かん！
R-7a.
７一飛だ
He rode it out!
（関係者５）しのいだ！
飛車と歩　たった２枚で！
With just a rook and a pawn?
And now Souya's on the attack.
（関係者６）
しかも手番が宗谷に！
This is where Shimada, 8-dan's, attack...
（零）ここで島田八段の攻めが—
ended
止まる！
and Master Souya's counterattack began.
宗谷名人の反撃が始まった
（藤本）勝負あったな…
That's the match.
I'm going to the waiting room.
控え室に行く
（島田）ああ…　雪だ…
Snow.
どんなにもがいても—
No matter how much I struggle,
容赦なく埋め尽くしてくる
it'll bury me without mercy.
It's a blinding darkness that dazzles my eyes.
目もくらむような まぶしい闇
Silent and overwhelming...
静かで圧倒的な…
It's captivatingly beautiful.
心奪われるほど美しい あの…
Wait.
（零）待って…
Please wait.
（零）待ってください！
It's not over yet.
まだ終わってません！
What?
His fortress was torn down, and his king is in danger.
矢倉(やぐら)は剥がされ 玉(ぎょく)も不安定
しかも相手は宗谷
Not to mention, his opponent is Souya.
ここから
ひっくり返るわけがなかろう
There's no way he can turn it around from here.
But it's not over yet!
（零）でも まだ終わってません！
Shimada still has pieces on the board!
島田さんの駒は生きてます！
It's over. Shimada is done.
終わりだよ！　島田はもう！
And it's because of their gap in skill.
しかも圧倒的な大差でな
Four straight losses!
４タテだ！
He's too weak!
力が足りな過ぎだ！
You're in Shimada's workshop, aren't you?
お前 確か
島田の研究会に入ってるよな？
I understand you don't want to admit your mentor's in a pinch,
先輩のピンチを
認めたくないのは分かるが—
かえって島田の株を落とすぞ
but you'll damage his reputation.
So shut up.
黙ってろ！
Well, Shimada, 8-dan, did his best.
（観客１）
いや 島田八段も頑張ったよ
Yeah...
（観客２）ああ…
But his opponent...
（観客３）でもな 相手がなぁ…
There's nothing he could've done. He was outclassed.
（観客４）
しかたないよ　相手が悪いよ
After all, it was Souya.
（観客５）宗谷だもんな
Four straight losses...
（観客６）４タテかぁ…
Still...
（観客７）あーあ それにしても…
He could've at least won once.
（観客８）１勝くらいな…
I wanted him to show some backbone.
（観客９）
意地見せてほしかったよなぁ
He didn't show us anything.
（観客10）いいとこ無しでしたね
Not unexpected.
（観客11）やっぱりな…
Yamagata was a long way off.
（観客12）山形は遠いね
Well, this is how it is.
（観客13）ま こんなもんでしょ
No.
（零）いや…
No, that's not right.
いや 違う…
To me, this board isn't dead yet.
まだ この盤面は
死んだようには思えない
島田さんの駒が死んだとは
僕には…
I don't think...
Shimada's pieces...
have died!
思えない
To me...
僕には…　僕には…
僕には！
（司会）
あ 桐山五段？　桐… どこへ？
Kiriyama, 5-dan?
Kiri... Where are you...
桐山五段！
Kiriyama, 5-dan!
（零）島田さん…
Shimada.
島田さん
Shimada!
島田さんっ！
Shogi Dragon Fujimoto!
藤本棋竜！
Shimada...
（零）島田… さん
Shimada, 8-dan, conceded.
（藤本）島田八段　投了だ
大差だよ 大差！
It's the gap in skill between them.
It's just like I said.
言ったとおりだろうが！
It wasn't noticed, huh?
（宗谷(そうや)冬司(とうじ)）気付かなかったね…
This darkness isn't just playing on an endless loop.
（島田）この闇は
ループしているだけではない
（観客１）おい 待てよ
Hey, wait.
（観客２）うん　これ…
Yeah.
This...
This B*7i move...
He turned the match around.
（観客４）逆転してる
The N*2d threatmate is gone too.
（観客５）
２四桂(けい)の詰めろも消してるし
（観客６）
あれ？ 宗谷名人の王
詰んでたんじゃないか？
Huh?
Isn't Master Souya's king under check?
With just one move,
（島田）その たった一手で—
the world took on an entirely different form.
世界はまるで違う姿を現す
死地に 一瞬
かいま見えていたはずの—
As I fell down the chasm to my almost certain death,
I saw a small flash of light.
せん光のような活路
You have too much faith in me.
（宗谷）君は僕を信用し過ぎだ
And it was so beautiful...
美しかったのに…
（零）
こうして獅子王戦は
島田さんの４連敗で幕を閉じた
And so, the Lion King Tournament came to a close after Shimada's four consecutive losses.
そして 島田さんと僕は
その夜のうちに京都をたった
That night, we left Kyoto.
Shimada, have some water and a light meal.
（零）島田さん
お水と軽い食べ物を…
Looking at his exhausted profile made me think of the path he's taken.
（零）その疲弊しきった横顔に—
僕は
彼の歩いてきた道のりを思った
That's right.
（零）そうだ…
分かっていたのだ　初めから
I've known it all along.
嵐の向こうにあるもの
それは…
What lies on the other side of the storm...
is just an even more furious storm.
ただ… 更に激しいだけの嵐なのだ
No matter how many times you fall,
you have to pick up the scattered fragments of yourself.
倒れても 倒れても
飛び散った自分のかけらを
かき集め—
This is a world where you continuously
pick yourself back up and move forward.
何度でも立ち上がり 進む者の世界
It's wandering without end.
終わりのない ほうこう
"Then why?"
ならば なぜ？
I can no longer ask that question to this profile I see before me.
その答えは　決して
この横顔に問うてはならない
Instead, I have to ask myself that question in the middle of that storm.
その答えは あの嵐の中で
自らに問うしかないのだ
Kyoto (Part 3)
Your fingers, your chest, your eyes
Are so dazzling there are nights when I get dizzy
They suddenly fall upon me, and it's just so warm
That it feels like I swallowed a seven-colored star
You held me tight, troubling me like a burning spark would
But I was taught to keep walking despite everything
God, please hear me out
For just a little while
Please connect us like that constellation
So that we're never away from each other
So that we're always together
Next Episode Preview
Episode 21
It's just like I said.
（島田）
だから言ったのに　俺は雨男だって
I'm a rain-bringer.
Just go and let everyone cheer you up!
（神宮寺）
どーんとみんなに
励ましてもらってこいよ
The petals have mostly fallen,
but I think I like it like this.
（あかり）もうだいぶ
散ってきちゃったけれど—
お姉ちゃん
このくらいの方が好きかな
I-I lost.
（横溝(よこみぞ)億泰(おくやす)）う… 負けました
I'm extremely delighted.
（二海堂）
恐悦至極にございます！
Illustration: Hara Testsuo
（三角）
まさかのピンチヒッターで
封じ手の開封とは！
I can't believe I had to reveal the sealed
move like some kind of pinch hitter.
You can't miss next week's
"March comes in like a lion"!
３月のライオン
次回もお見逃しなく！
いちごちゃ〜ん！　今 帰るよ〜
Strawberry! I'm coming home!